<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: raspberry pi | milkandtang]]></title>
  <link href="http://milkandtang.com/blog/categories/raspberry-pi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://milkandtang.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-07T20:38:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://milkandtang.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathan Wittstock]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting WiFi on a Headless Raspberry Pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://milkandtang.com/blog/2013/08/27/getting-wifi-on-a-headless-raspberry-pi/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-27T11:38:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://milkandtang.com/blog/2013/08/27/getting-wifi-on-a-headless-raspberry-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the final steps in a to-be-announced project involved getting a headless <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/">Raspberry Pi</a> up on WiFi at boot time—which turned out to be a little more challenging that first expected. Not because it was particularly difficult, but because the documentation was poor.</p>

<p>Below are my full configuration files that were required. The WiFi USB dongle itself was an <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/products/1030">Adafruit USB WiFi with Antenna</a> which is actually a B-LINK BBL-LW05-AR5; notable becuase of its sizeable antenna, and for working with the latest Raspbian Wheezy distribution.</p>

<p>Prior to getting started, make sure your Raspbian is up to date by issuing:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get upgrade
</code></p>

<p>At that point, reboot and connect your WiFi module to USB. Then, edit your config. It's worth noting that I have an interface <code>eth0</code> which is set to DHCP, and my <code>wlan0</code> interface which has a static IP. This allows me to use ethernet as a failsafe if something goes wrong.</p>

<p>First, in the file <code>/etc/network/interfaces</code>:</p>

<p>```
auto lo</p>

<p>iface lo inet loopback
iface eth0 inet dhcp</p>

<p>allow-hotplug wlan0
iface wlan0 inet manual
wpa-roam /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf</p>

<p>iface YOUR_WIFI_ID inet static
address 192.168.1.5
netmask 255.255.255.0
gateway 192.168.1.1</p>

<h1>iface default inet dhcp</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>This is setting up your ethernet to dhcp, your wifi to manual, sourcing the <code>wpa_supplicant.conf</code> file, and then assigning your named Wireless connection to a static IP. Note that <em>YOUR_WIFI_ID</em> above should be an identifier you make up yourself. For example, mine is <em>NORTH_WPA</em>.</p>

<p>Now, configure the network information in <code>/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf</code>:</p>

<p>```
ctrl_interface=DIR=/var/run/wpa_supplicant GROUP=netdev</p>

<h1>update_config=1</h1>

<p>network={</p>

<pre><code>ssid="Your SSID Name"
proto=RSN
key_mgmt=WPA-PSK
pairwise=CCMP TKIP
group=CCMP TKIP
psk="Your WPA Password"
id_str="YOUR_WIFI_ID"
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Again, note that <em>YOUR_WIFI_ID</em> is present.</p>

<p>At that point, reboot. Assuming you've got all your information correct (and that your key management and etc. match mine) you'll be connected automatically at boot!</p>

<p>Much of the information in this post was gleaned from <a href="http://pingbin.com/2012/12/setup-wifi-raspberry-pi/">this thread</a>. The original poster's information didn't work for me, but I was able to assemble a working config from various commenters' information.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
